<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A True reporte of the taking of the great towne and castell of Polotzko by the King of Polonia with the manner of the assaults, batteries, undermininges, skirmishes and fyreworkes, that were there vsed from the 11 of August to the 30 of the same month 1579.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20092.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4832</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23946721</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23946721</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09828)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1839:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A True reporte of the taking of the great towne and castell of Polotzko by the King of Polonia with the manner of the assaults, batteries, undermininges, skirmishes and fyreworkes, that were there vsed from the 11 of August to the 30 of the same month 1579.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint from colophon; place of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸.</note>
                  <note>T.p. contains illustration.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poland --  History --  Stephen Bathory, 1575-1586.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26997:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 154 -->
            <p>
               <hi>¶A true Reporte of the <hi>taking of the great towne</hi>
               </hi> and Caſtell of <hi>Polotzko,</hi> by the King of <hi>Polonia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVith the manner of the Aſſaults,</hi> Batteries, Vndermininges, Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes and Fyreworkes, that were there vſed, from the 11. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> to the .30 of the ſame Month. 1579.</p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26997:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 155 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26997:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 155 -->
            <head>¶ A true Reporte of the <hi>taking of the Towne and</hi> Caſtell of Polotzko, by the King of Polonia, the 30. of Auguſt 1579.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He laſt of Iune</hi> the King of <hi>Polonia</hi> beinge at a Towne called <hi>Wilde,</hi> brake vp his Siege and came to <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> to muſter there: in whiche place, his Maieſtie called toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Lordes and Captaines and men of warre, to know after what order they ſhould prouide for the ſafegarde and defence of their Countrey, and how for to keepe the enimie, which was the <hi>Moſcoue</hi> furre from them, and
<pb facs="tcp:26997:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 156 -->
there his Maieſtie agreed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeege the Citie of <hi>Polotzko,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that Towne lyeth in the border of the great Dukedome of <hi>Litto,</hi> and principallye of the Towne of <hi>Villo,</hi> and there lyeth no Fortreſſe betweene that and the <hi>Wilde,</hi> and if he had not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the waye to the ſame Citie, he ſhould haue geuen his enemie waye to haue entered into the Dukedome of <hi>Litto,</hi> and alſo to the <hi>Wilde:</hi> and therfore his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie found it needefull to looke to, becauſe he tooke this war in hande, not onelye to recouer that ſame Towne to the Crowne of <hi>Poland</hi> againe, as it hath beene in times paſt: but to withſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enimiy, &amp; to keepe him back. In his Country, the winter is very hard, with verye great raines, ſnowes, fogges and continuall
<pb facs="tcp:26997:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 156 -->
troſtes: and therefore very peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to make war, in which the king of <hi>Poland</hi> hath found verye daingerous in paſſing from the <hi>VVilde</hi> to the ſaide Cittie of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotzko,</hi> by reaſon of the clammye ground, with the great thawes and caines, and deepe ryuers, with the great trouble of his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryage, of his great ordinaunce, powder, ſhot, munition, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde of artillerye, with the loſſe of his horſes and other bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes for want of ſuſtenaunce tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing thoſe barrame wildernes and heigh mountaines: yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could diſcorage this migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty prince fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taking of this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe in hand, although manye of his Noble men and wiſe Captai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes did ſhow what perill it were for him to paſſe with ſo great an Armye, and telling of him the
<pb facs="tcp:26997:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 157 -->
ſtrength of the Towne and the Caſtell with all other inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunces: yet could hee not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded from his opinion, but rather the more encouraged, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered his people together: and hoping that if hee could take that Towne, it would be a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to his enimies and a great incouragement to his owne Soldiors: becauſe this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is the ſtrongeſt and greateſt in all his Dominions. And his Maieſtie did ſend out of <hi>Suero,</hi> the honorable <hi>Nicolaum Radzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nil,</hi> chiefe Gouernour of the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne called the <hi>Wilde,</hi> with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Horſemen &amp; Foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with a certain nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garians:</hi> with the Honorable <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Bekize</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citie of <hi>Polotzko,</hi> to ſtoppe the high wayes, that there might com no ſuccour from
<pb facs="tcp:26997:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 157 -->
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince of <hi>Muſcoue.</hi> And for al that he tooke great paines for to be ſodenly there: yet the wayes was ſo fowle, and the paſſages ſo crooked, that it was long or euer that they could come there. And becauſe that the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> had ſent defyaunce to the <hi>Muſcouo</hi> King: hee doubting of the beſiege of them of <hi>Polotzko,</hi> ſent <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>yde to them of <hi>Polotzko,</hi> which came two daies before the Honorable <hi>Nicolaue</hi> came there: but hee comming thither did ſo ſtoppe the paſſages, that he could ſend no more ſuccoures thether. And immediatlye after the King of <hi>Polon</hi> with his whole campe ordinaunce, bag and baggage, with great paines, hauing fowle wayes, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> continual raine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fell and the fowle wether, was conſtrained to make very ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:26997:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 158 -->
i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rneyes: and in the meane tyme his forewarde tooke three Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels, called, <hi>Coſianua, Craſne</hi> and <hi>Situo,</hi> in their iorney, which they quickly ſpoyled and burnt. And the 11. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> his Majeſtie with all his power came neere to the Tower of <hi>Polozko,</hi> and pyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched his Campe not far from the Walles of the Towne: and then his Maieſtie cauſed his Campe in three places to bee intrenched againſt the Towne. And as the Towne being very ſtrongly fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with very ſtrong Bulwarks and other Fortreſſes, and being very well prouided of all manner powder ſhot and other Engines, and putting great confidence in the Caſtell which ſtoode without the Towne: iſſued out of the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne, and forced the king of <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> to withdraw him ſelfe from that
<pb facs="tcp:26997:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 158 -->
parte of the Towne where the Subber<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s were, in which place the Caſtell ſtoode: but in the end the <hi>Polanes</hi> had the victorye, and chaeed the <hi>Moſcoes</hi> into the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne &amp; the Caſtell, &amp; ſet the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barbes a fyre. And in ſhorte time wholly deſtroyed it. And after this they did dayly vnder minde the ground, till they came vnder the cheefe gate of the Caſtell: but the almyghtye God at this time ſhewed his mightye power, for manye dayes, without ceaſſing, we had great raynes: ſo that all laboure and diligence of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dior was hindered: yet for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre that they had to ouercome their enimyes nothing could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them: but dayly they did their endeuor againſt the towne and Caſtell. And thoſe within the Towne and the Caſtel, although
<pb facs="tcp:26997:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 159 -->
their enimy with out was fearce and daily did ſhoot at them with great ordinaunce, and neuer c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed daye nor night ſhooting and throwing of wilde fyre into the Towne, and although their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were couered with ſtrawe and reede, and ſuch thinges apte to take fyre: yet they nothing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayde, did daylye defende them ſelues with making prouiſion with raw Hydes and other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges fit for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> purpoſe, for to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the violence of the fyre: and verye valiantlye defended both the Towne and Caſtell, and as faſt as anye was ſtroken downe, an other would ſteppe ouer him, and fyght ſtoutly in his roome: wherby it is ſeene that the <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coues</hi> are verye valiaunt in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of a Holde: yet at the length GOD of his mercy ſhewed vs a
<pb facs="tcp:26997:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 159 -->
fayre day. For the 29. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> our people with great diligence, and no ſmall perill, waded tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the ryuer, carying wilde fyre in one hand, and their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon in the other, and manfullye runne vp the Hill, and made an aſſaulte to the breces of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell, &amp; ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on fyre, and ſo with the ſhooting of the ordinaunce on the one ſide, &amp; the caſting of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre on the other, the enimie was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to forſake the Bulwarke, and to retyre, which gaue our Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors ſuch courage, that they did follow the enimye thorowe the fyre, and thought to winne the Caſtell: but they did fayle of their purpoſe, becauſe the force of the fyre was great, and the force of the enimy greater, they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to retyre with the loſſe of 27. of their menne, and verye manye
<pb facs="tcp:26997:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 160 -->
wounded: And of our enimyes were ſlaine 200. The verye ſame daye the enimy did make a ſygne as though hee would haue yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but they ment nothing leſſe: For they had prouided new Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes, and blinded our menne with the flames of fyre: therefore the Kinges Maieſtie was fullye bent to ſhow the vttermoſt that he coulde doe, becauſe the enimye ſhoulde haue no tyme to fortifye him. And therefore the next daye beinge the 30. daye of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> he cauſed all his armye, aſwell Horſemen as footemen, to make an aſſault to the Town: and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed certaine Horſemen and Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to make an aſſaulte to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parte of the Towne, where they had vndermined the Wall, and throw downe a great peece of it, and ſet fyre one parte of the
<pb facs="tcp:26997:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 160 -->
Caſtell: and the place where they were the day before they recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, where they found the <hi>Muſco</hi> digging and defending of him ſelfe: but the <hi>Polon</hi> droue him backe, and had him wholy in his power: and ſo the king of <hi>Polon</hi> being mooued with pittye, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſhed any chriſtian blood did giue pardon to all them that he found in the Caſtell, and them that would ſerue, hee tooke into ſeruice, which was a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, becauſe they would ſaue their goodes, &amp; they that would, hee gaue them ſafe conduct to go into <hi>Moſcoui,</hi> and thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would not yeelde wer theſe: the honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Baſilius Iuanowitz, Telateuſki Nicole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſki Demetrius Michalowitz Schitbathi, Oholeuſki, Matthe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anowitz: Rzowki. Iwan Hrecho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riowitz, Suſin, Petrus Inanowitz:
<pb facs="tcp:26997:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 161 -->
VVolenſki Lutzian, Tretiakow, Kakouſe:</hi> whiche were all Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and Officers in the town and Caſtel, and therfore the king tooke them forceablye priſoners, and garded the Towne and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell with his owne Soldiors. The nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the <hi>Moſcoues</hi> that defended the Caſtell, were 6000. which moſte parte was ſlaine and found dead in dyches, and of them in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Towne, there was no certaine number known, becauſe a great number fled. And alſo there was found within yse town and Caſtell ſuch ſtore of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, with powder, ſhot, and lead, and all other kinde of Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerye, that there was thought there was not the like Towne nor Caſtell in Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>And therfore his Maieſty ſeeing that GOD hath geuen him ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:26997:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 161 -->
victory ouer his enimyes, more then he deſerued or looked for, gaue commaundement tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough all his Realme, to geue God praiſe and thankes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted. 1579.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
